and optimization similar to inlining as
far as benefits are concerned is called
function call inlining and it takes code
that calls a function
so we do some work then we prepare the
function parameters for example put them
in the right registers
according to the calling convention then
we call a function
and then we do more work after that and
when we call a function
let's say that the function itself was
just adding the first two parameters and
putting
that in the return value and then
returning so this sends us back here
and then we continue with the more work
so this is what a normal function call
looks like
so now we can try to avoid the overheads
of calling the function and returning
from it
by doing our work then we don't have to
prepare the function parameters anymore
now what we do is we simply take the
work of the function
and just plug it in here so in this case
we add up adding
the registers for example that did
contain the values that we eventually
ended up passing here so we didn't need
to copy these registers to a0 and a1
and we put the result exactly where we
needed for example
r7 instead of having to maybe copy from
rv
to r7 and then we can continue
with our work so the first benefit of
function call inlining
is that it eliminates the calling and
returning overheads
which include not only the function call
instruction
and the return instructions themselves
but
also the code that prepares the function
parameters according to the calling
convention
and the code that possibly in the
function itself needs to for example pop
parameters from the stack and so on
and then possibly also the work here
after we return
to get the return value into the
register where we need it
all of that can be done by simply
inlining the function and then just
using the registers we want
and just like loop unrolling which
helped scheduling
do better so does function call inlining
because really what we have is this is
where we can do scheduling
and then we need to call the function so
these instructions cannot be moving
around beyond this point
we can do scheduling here but again we
cannot do much of this work before the
call
and then the function itself can be
scheduled
but we have to do it within this we have
three separate pieces of code
each of which can be scheduled but we
cannot for example take something from
here
and use it to fill an empty slot here on
the other hand
after inlining this is just code with no
function calls or anything
so now all of this work is schedulable
for example the work from the function
can
easily be moved around assuming that the
dependency is allowed
so inlining also lets us do better
scheduling
just like loop unrolling did and for the
same reason now we have
more work that we can play with just
like
loop unrolling the elimination of the
overheads for calling returning and so
on
will reduce the number of instructions
the better scheduling
will let us reduce the cpi and that
means that we can usually improve the
execution time by quite a bit
the smaller the function the more
benefit from both of these
because if the function is very small
the overheads of calling and returning
are high relative to the work we are
actually doing
and also if the function is small
scheduling within the function is not
going to do much
but if we put it into the existing code
suddenly this instruction here can
probably be squeezed into an existing
cycle without really adding another
cycle
and finally there is a downside to
inlining and it's very similar to what
we had for loop unrolling